Guide to the Earl Barnes Papers
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Earl Barnes papers
1882-1912
SC0109
Barnes, Earl, 1861-1935.
2 Linear feet
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Provenance
Gift of Joseph Barnes, 1957; transferred to University Archives in 1973.
Information about Access
None.
BIOGRAPHY
Earl Barnes was born in Martville, New York, on July 15, 1861. He married Mary Sheldon (b. 1850) in either 1884 or 1885 while he was still in school. Barnes received an A.B. from Indiana University in 1889 and an M.S. from Cornell in 1891. He held a position as Professor of History at Indiana University in 1889. When David Starr Jordan was appointed President of Stanford University in 1891, he took Earl Barnes with him as Professor of Education. Barnes and his wife Mary Sheldon Barnes taught at Stanford until 1897, when Barnes was asked by Jordan to resign. Jordan had discovered that Barnes had been involved in an extramarital love affair, conduct which the President of Stanford University could not tolerate in one of his faculty members. Barnes and wife went to Europe, where Mary Sheldon Barnes died in 1898. In 1900 Barnes remarried; his second wife was Anna Kohler, by whom he had four children --Joseph, Howard, Bernard, and Mary. After leaving Stanford Barnes never again held a position in an American university. He was appointed staff lecturer, London Society for Extension of University Teaching for the year 1900-01, but after that supported himself as a free-lance lecturer and writer. During his later years he resided in New Hartford, Connecticut, where he died on May 29, 1935.
His major publications are:
Studies in Education, 2v. 1897
Where Knowledge Fails, 1907
Women in Modern Society, 1912
Psychology of Childhood and Youth, 1914.
SCOPE AND CONTENT
The material in this collection was part of a gift made to the Library in 1957 of books formerly belonging to Earl Barnes. Earl Barnes' son Joseph was the donor. These books and other materials, since they all dealt with education, were stored in the Education Library from 1957-1973, at which latter date 9 scrapbooks and approximately 1/2 linear feet of unbound material were transferred to the Archives.
Seven of the nine scrapbooks deal generally with the subject of child psychology and development. They illustrate Prof. Barnes' areas of research interest (1882-1897) and contain numerous research notes and case histories, as well as some correspondence and reprints of scholarly articles. [BOXES 1-3]
The eighth scrapbook contains clippings, correspondence, programs, etc. (1894-1896) about Earl Barnes and the California Teachers Association. The ninth scrapbook contains articles clipped from the London Daily News(1907-1908) dealing with famous British personalities. [BOX 3]
The last group of material deals with race relations, 1892-1912. These items are not bound into a scrapbook. They consist of clippings (pasted onto sheets of paper); articles, either reprints or clipped from journals; some reviews; and some short bibliographies compiled by Prof. Barnes. Although the subject of most clippings is the status of the Black man in America, there are also clippings about Haiti and South Africa. [BOX 4]
Access Terms
Barnes, Earl, 1861-1935.; California State Teachers Association..; Stanford University. Graduate School of Education. -- General subdivision--Faculty.;; Child development--Research.; Child psychology.; Race relations.
Collection Contents
- Scrapbook of material on child development, with an author and subject index. Includes notes from lectures; samples of research survey forms; some correspondence., 1882-94 (Box 1)
- Scrapbook of material on child development, with emphasis on study of color perception and discrimination. Contents include research data and sample questionnaire forms., 1891-95 (Box 1)
- Scrapbook of material on child development, with emphasis on study of imaginary companions created by children. Contents include reprints of articles on the subject; collected research papers; sample questionnaire forms; data on case studies supplied by volunteers., 1892-95 (Box 1)
- Scrapbook of material on child development, with emphasis on study of fears experienced by children. Contents include case histories and sample questionnaire forms., 1889-91 (Box 2)
- Scrapbook of material on child development, with an author and subject index. Contents include reprints of articles, correspondence, course syllabi, sample observation forms., 1894-96 (Box 2)
- Scrapbook of material on child development, with emphasis on study of religious and ethical concepts in children. Contents consist mostly of case histories. (Box 2)
- Scrapbook of material on child development, with emphasis on study of the development of poetic instinct in children. Contents include samples of children's poems; a few items of correspondence; some reprints of articles on poetry., 1890-97 (Box 3)
- Scrapbook of material on Earl Barnes and the California State Teachers Association, Contents include clippings; some correspondence; programs of meetings. Of special interest are a few items on the fee structure for the experimental kindergarten on campus run by the Dept. of Education., 1894-96 (Box 3)
- Scrapbook of clippings from the London Daily News, The clippings were "The Man of the Week" articles, dealing with famous personalities of the day (mostly British)., 1907-08 (Box 3)
- Race relations--miscellaneous material. Contents include the following: (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Articles
    - "The American Negro and race blending," by Frances Hoggan, Oct-09
    - "The tragedy of the mulatto," by Ray Stannard Baker, Apr 1898
    - "Race characteristics as determining factors in education", by Dr. J.T. Searcy, Jul, 1891
  - Bulletins
    - The Southern Workman, vol. XXXI, no. 10, published by Hampton Institute Press., October 1902
    - The Bulletin of Atlanta University, no. 5, Dec 1893
    - The Institute for Colored Youth, Philadelphia, (informational booklet), 1832-1903
  - Miscellaneous clippings.
- Race relations--"Negro leaders", 1892-1912 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  Clippings on Henry 0. Tanner, Paul L. Dunbar, Joshua A. Brockett, H.R. Revels, Sir Conrad Reeves, Emma Wilson, Henry P. Chatham, the Jubilee Singers [photo]. Also ALS to Earl Barnes from D.E. Tobias, Oct. 14, 19XX; Article--"What America owes to the Negro," by James Weldon Johnson, n.d.
- Race relations--miscellaneous, [1901-1912] (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous clippings.
- Race relations--"Race hatred, violence", [1892-1907] (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous clippings.
- Race relations--"Negro crime"; "Negro in Africa", [1903-1907] (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous clippings, one book review.
- Race relations--miscellaneous, 1907-1911 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Miscellaneous clippings.
  - Tract by D.E. Tobias, "Freed, but not free; the grievances of the Afro-American", London, [contains Barnes' comments (holograph) on Tobias' character]., 1899
- Race relations--"Southern conditions", [1899-1907] (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - miscellaneous clippings.
  - printed speech - "The bright side of the Negro problem" by Rev. Chas. V. Monk, n.d.
  - articles -
    - "The southern people during reconstruction" by Thomas Nelson Page, 1901
    - "Following the color line," by Ray Stannard Baker, (series of 4 articles), 1907
    - "The new southern statesman," by Ray Stannard Baker, [1907?]
    - "Can the south solve the Negro problem?" by Carl Shurz, Jan-04
    - "The Negro: the southerner's problem," by Thomas Nelson Page, 1904
    - "The great American question; the special plea of a Southerner," by Thomas Nelson Page, n.d.
    - "Some aspects of the race problem in the South," by Robert F. Campbell, 1899
- Race relations--"the Negro in politics", [1901-1905] (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - miscellaneous clippings
- Race relations--"Negro bibliography", [1890-1902] (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - miscellaneous clipped reviews; bibliographical entries made by Earl Barnes.
- Race relations--"Hayti", [1902-1908] (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - miscellaneous clippings
- Race relations--"Negro education", [1894-1908] (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - miscellaneous clippings.
  - Earl Barnes' personal research notes (typed and holograph)
  - TLS. Hincks, John H. (Dean of Atlanta Univ.) to Barnes, re. sources for info on Negro education., Mar 7, 1894
  - Yearbook of the Georgia State Industrial College, 1907-08
  - "Education of colored children," n.d. (chapter VII, from the 24th biennial report of the Dept. of Public Instruction [Indiana?])
  - "A new phase of industrial education; the school," by Isabel C. Barrows, 1906
- Race relations--"Wilmington lynching", [1903] (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - miscellaneous clippings
- Race relations--"Negro and industry", [1899-1903] (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - miscellaneous clippings.
  - article - "Colored men as cotton manufacturers," by Jerome Dowd, Sep-02
- Race relations--"Chautauqua discussion,", [1903] (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - miscellaneous clippings
- Race relations--"Race theories", [1901-1906] (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - miscellaneous clippings.
  - article - "Race questions and prejudice," International Journal of Ethics, Apr-06
  - Rudyard Kipling's "The White Man's Burden" text of and reaction to.